<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Open Source GIS Data</title>
    <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com" />
    <updated>2023-01-19T16:17:43-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Importance of Open Source GIS software</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/importance-of-open-source-gis-software.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/importance-of-open-source-gis-software.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/11/nasa-earth-from-low-earth-orbit-at-night.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="Resources"/>
            <category term="GIS"/>

        <updated>2023-01-18T16:24:24-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/11/nasa-earth-from-low-earth-orbit-at-night.jpg" alt="" />
                    Geographic information systems (GIS) is a series of computer programs that link geographic features in a database with information about them. This allows users to map out data, analyze it, and share the results. The use of open source GIS software can save companies money&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/11/nasa-earth-from-low-earth-orbit-at-night.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p class="msg msg--highlight ">Geographic information systems (GIS) is a series of computer programs that link geographic features in a database with information about them. This allows users to map out data, analyze it, and share the results. The use of open source GIS software can save companies money and allow greater flexibility than proprietary GIS systems do. </p>
<h2>Open Source GIS Software is an Alternative to Proprietary GIS Software.</h2>
<p>Proprietary GIS software is expensive, whereas open source GIS software is free. Open source GIS software can be run on a variety of operating systems, whereas proprietary systems are only available for one or two operating systems. Open source systems often have similar functionality and quality to proprietary products.</p>
<h2>Open Source Software is Free and Does Not Have Restrictions on Use or Redistribution.</h2>
<p>It can be used for any purpose, including commercial applications, without paying any fees to the author or copyright holder. Additionally, open source GIS software can be modified and redistributed as it is under a license that permits this type of activity.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The idea of free GIS software isn't new; Esri was founded in 1969 specifically to develop and distribute such products after finding that many customers were using public domain systems.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In fact, many modern GIS technologies are built on top of open source code such as PostgreSQL or MySQL databases—both of which provide their source code freely as well.</p>
<h2>Open Source Means That the Original Source Code is Available for Users to Modify and Adapt to Suit Their Needs.</h2>
<p>Open source software is free to use. It allows you to see the source code, modify it and adapt it to suit your needs. You can also share and redistribute open source software with others. </p>
<p>If you want to distribute a modified version of an open source program, you may do so as long as you comply with both the terms of the license that covers your use of the original program and any other applicable law in doing so (e.g., fair use). The most common form of open-source software license is known as “copyleft” licensing which requires those who distribute modified versions of copyrighted works based on copylefted material must make their modifications available under similar terms for others receiving such a copy or derivative work from them; however, certain licenses are permissive in allowing redistribution without this requirement if reproduced on another medium or if distributed with an accompanying text file containing information required by law (such as copyrights).</p>
<h2>GIS Allows Users to Map Out Data, Analyze it, and Share the Results.</h2>
<p>GIS alongside open-source programming languages allows users to map out data, analyze it, and share the results. GIS programs can be used for a variety of tasks, such as mapping crime rates across cities or determining whether certain areas have adequate access to fresh water. These applications are often very specific in nature and require highly skilled programmers to create them—therefore making GIS software proprietary software is not financially feasible for most companies who would benefit from its use. </p>
<p>Open source GIS programs provide a solution by allowing anyone with access to the internet or a computer running Windows OS or Mac OS X operating systems with an internet connection to use these powerful tools at no cost.</p>
<h2>Proprietary GIS Software is Expensive</h2>
<p>Open source GIS software is free and doesn’t require you to pay any licensing fees. Proprietary GIS software, on the other hand, requires payment of licensing fees. One of the main advantages of open source GIS software is that it can be freely used, modified, and redistributed with no limitation or restriction. This allows users to customize the program as they see fit. Open source GIS also aid in collaboration because multiple people can work on the same projects at once without having to share files back and forth.</p>
<h2>Open Source GIS Can Do the Same Work as Proprietary GIS but Without Additional Costs.</h2>
<p>Open source GIS software often has similar capabilities as proprietary GIS programs but you don't have to pay any money upfront or per use. For example, an open source version of ArcGIS called QGIS performs nearly identically to ArcMap and does not cost anything and can be installed on as many computers as you want. Anyone with access to the internet and a modern computer can download and install QGIS.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Open source GIS software is an incredibly powerful tool, and it can do the same work as proprietary GIS. However, open source won't cost you anything to use or manage. You can download and install open source programs for free without paying any license fees to a vendor. Open source GIS software is an alternative to proprietary GIS software. This means that it can do the same work as proprietary GIS but without additional costs. Open source GIS also allows users to modify and adapt it to suit their needs, which makes it useful for many different applications.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How to Utilize Open Federal, State and Local GIS Data</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/how-to-utilize-open-federal-state-and-local-gis-data.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/how-to-utilize-open-federal-state-and-local-gis-data.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/10/patrick-tomasso-new-york.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="United States"/>
            <category term="US Federal"/>
            <category term="Resources"/>
            <category term="GIS"/>

        <updated>2023-01-18T19:16:38-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/10/patrick-tomasso-new-york.jpg" alt="" />
                    When you think of a geographic information system (GIS), you probably think of maps, charts and other visualizations. But there's more to GIS than just imagery—it can also be used as a tool for data discovery. In this post, we'll discuss how to unlock the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/10/patrick-tomasso-new-york.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>When you think of a geographic information system (GIS), you probably think of maps, charts and other visualizations. But there's more to GIS than just imagery—it can also be used as a tool for data discovery. In this post, we'll discuss how to unlock the potential of open federal, state and local GIS data by uncovering free federal data resources, exploring free state and local sources and learning how best to use them all together. </p>
<h2>Uncovering Free Federal Data Resources </h2>
<p>There is a wealth of open source GIS data available that can help with your work. Federal agencies are required to make their data open and accessible. Some of the best sources for open federal, state and local GIS data can be found open and available online in a format easy to view and download for processing. The following list highlights some federal, state and local sources of open GIS data and tools.</p>
<ul>
<li>USGS (United States Geological Survey)</li>
<li>NOAA (National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration)</li>
<li>EPA (Environmental Protection Agency)</li>
</ul>
<p>The federal, state and local governments all make available a wide variety of spatial data (that is, information that has a location associated with it). To help you find this valuable resource, the US government maintains an open data portal at www.data.gov that allows users to search for and download geospatial datasets from across the country. The site also offers links to other important resources such as the National Geospatial Program (NGP) and National Map Viewer. </p>
<p> </p>
<h2>Tips for Using Open Source GIS Data</h2>
<p>Know your data. Before you use open source GIS data in your project, take the time to understand the data and its limitations. Understanding the source of the data will help you determine what is and isn't a good candidate for your project, as well as how it can be used (or if it should even be used at all). While many open source datasets have metadata attached that describes their origin and quality, this information may not always be available or easy to find.</p>
<p>Understand copyright restrictions. Just because a dataset is made publicly available doesn't mean that anyone can do whatever they want with it immediately! You'll always want to pay attention to any copyright statements or licenses associated with an open source dataset before using it in your project. Be aware of whether there are any restrictions on how much money you can charge for any products created using their information, how many people are allowed access at once (with limits on concurrent users), whether commercial companies need additional licensing agreements before they use certain materials from these datasets, etcetera—these kinds of things exist within most of today's licenses governing digital content creation - so make sure they're not being overlooked while planning out future projects involving GIS software/data sets! </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>State of Florida GIS Data Sources</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/florida-data-sources.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/florida-data-sources.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/4/ryan-parker-miami-aerial.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="United States"/>
            <category term="Data Source"/>

        <updated>2023-01-19T16:17:43-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/4/ryan-parker-miami-aerial.jpg" alt="" />
                    Introduction The following page includes links to various geospatial data sources for the state of Florida. The majority of these data sources provide GIS data in formats compatible with ArcGIS and QGIS through the REST Services. The Florida GIS Portal is the state's official public&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/4/ryan-parker-miami-aerial.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h2 data-pm-slice="1 1 []">Introduction</h2>
<p>The following page includes links to various geospatial data sources for the state of Florida. The majority of these data sources provide GIS data in formats compatible with ArcGIS and QGIS through the REST Services. </p>
<h2><a href="https://geodata.floridagio.gov/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">https://geodata.floridagio.gov/</a></h2>
<p data-pm-slice="1 3 []">The <a href="https://geodata.floridagio.gov/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">Florida GIS Portal</a> is the state's official public website for geospatial data. It provides access to many different types of data, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Land Use Data (e.g., parcels, zoning)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Cadastral/property boundary data (e.g., parcel owners and addresses)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>State Facility Data (e.g., landfills, sewer systems)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Transportation Data (e.g., road networks)</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2>List of REST Services:</h2>
<div id="restServices"></div>
<p>
<script src="cartobin-state-api.js" reqstate="Florida"></script>
</p>
<h2 data-pm-slice="1 1 []">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This is the most comprehensive list of geospatial data sources for the state of Florida. We hope that you find this information useful, and we invite you to <a href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/contact-open-source-gis-data.html">contact us</a> with any questions or comments.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What is a Geographic Information System?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/what-is-a-geographic-information-system.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/what-is-a-geographic-information-system.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/1/deco-map.JPG" medium="image" />
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="Resources"/>
            <category term="GIS"/>

        <updated>2023-01-13T00:37:10-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/1/deco-map.JPG" alt="" />
                    How GIS components work together. A transformation based view of GIS operation, in Martin. D. (1995). Theories of GIS. Wikimedia Commons CC Image GIS stands for Geographic Information System. A GIS holds different types of geospatial data types like rasters, points, lines and polygons for visualization&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/1/deco-map.JPG" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h2><img loading="lazy" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6f/Fig_4.4.png" alt="diagram of how GIS components work together" data-is-external-image="true"></h2>
<p class="align-center">How GIS components work together. A transformation based view of GIS operation, in Martin. D. (1995). Theories of GIS. <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Fig_4.4.png" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Commons CC Image</a></p>
<h2>What is a GIS?</h2>
<p>GIS stands for <strong>Geographic Information System</strong>. A GIS holds different types of geospatial data types like rasters, points, lines and polygons for visualization and analysis. The technology of visualizing and analyzing geographic data can be applied to any industry and add value.</p>
<h2>What is GIS used for?</h2>
<p>GIS can be used to identify problems, monitor changes, manage and respond to events, perform forecasting, set priorities and to understand trends. GIS is used in many different industries including but not limited to environmental, emergency, urban planning, real estate, government, military, agriculture and many more.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c7/Snow-cholera-map.jpg" alt="The original map drawn by Dr. John Snow (1813-1858), a British physician who is one of the founders of medical epidemiology, showing cases of cholera in the London epidemics of 1854, clustered around the locations of water pumps." data-is-external-image="true"></p>
<p>The original map drawn by Dr. John Snow (1813-1858), a British physician who is one of the founders of medical epidemiology, showing cases of cholera in the London epidemics of 1854, clustered around the locations of water pumps. <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Snow-cholera-map.jpg" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Wikimedia Commons Public Domain Image</a></p>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Examples of GIS uses in different industries</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">Real estate agents use a GIS to visualize average home prices across different areas. Urban planners and developers use GIS to outline zones where certain types of buildings and amenities will be placed in cities and neighborhoods. The military uses GIS to plan missions and monitor situations like movements of troops and equipment.</p>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">What data can be used in a GIS?</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">A GIS requires spatial data, or data that is tied to a specific location on Earth. Satellite data is often the first type of data that comes to mind when thinking about GIS. Using satellite data users are able to see what the world looks like the time the images where captured and how it may have changed if there were previous images taken. Polygon data is often used to show country, state, city and municipal boundaries. A line might be used to show a road or a river. A single point or a collection of points might be used to show where events happened or where something is located.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Cartobin GIS Servers Web App</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/cartobin-gis-servers-web-app.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/cartobin-gis-servers-web-app.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/8/globe-map.webp" medium="image" />
            <category term="Resources"/>
            <category term="About"/>

        <updated>2023-01-13T16:19:13-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/8/globe-map.webp" alt="" />
                    What is Cartobin? Cartobin is a web application developed by Ben Millard. He was inspired to create the application by Jeff from mappingsupport.com who created and maintains a very large list of GIS rest servers. The application provides an interface to interact with the list&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/8/globe-map.webp" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">What is Cartobin?</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">Cartobin is a web application developed by Ben Millard. He was inspired to create the application by Jeff from mappingsupport.com who created and maintains a very large list of GIS rest servers. The application provides an interface to interact with the list by creating pages for the different categories. There is a State category, a category US Federal sources and another category for miscellaneous sources.</p>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Special Thanks to Ben</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">I want to give a special thanks to Ben Millard for creating this application and the API that serves the data. After posting on Reddit about the Open Source GIS Data State Index he reached out giving me permission to use the API. I was able to create a short vanilla javascipt script that fetches data from his API and displays it on the <a href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/state/index.html">state pages.</a> This allowed me to easily add hundreds of GIS rest servers to the website for every single state.</p>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Plans for the future</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">At the time of posting this article I have not yet integrated the Federal data sources from the API in the website. My next course of action is to add the federal sources and the other miscellaneous sources. All of the sources from the API and the list are GIS rest servers. The initial sources published on this website were Geo Portals or geospatial data search engines for different organizations within states. The plan is to integrate the API for the rest servers and continue to add Geo Portals and other miscellaneous sources that are not just rest servers. Beyond just finding and adding sources I will create content around some of the most useful and interesting resources that are recommended to me or that I find.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>United States Data Sources</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/united-states-data-sources.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/united-states-data-sources.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/2/USA.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="United States"/>
            <category term="Resources"/>
            <category term="Data Source"/>

        <updated>2023-01-13T00:15:43-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/2/USA.png" alt="" />
                    Click on the map to be redirected to the results pages for that state.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/2/USA.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="900" height="525" style="border: none;" src="https://createaclickablemap.com/map.php?&amp;id=113426&amp;maplocation=false&amp;online=true"></iframe></div>Click on the map to be redirected to the results pages for that state. 
<script>
	if (window.addEventListener) {
		window.addEventListener("message", function(event) {
			if (event.data.length >= 22) {
				if (event.data.substr(0, 22) == "__MM-LOCATION.REDIRECT") location = event.data.substr(22);
			}
		}, false);
	} else if (window.attachEvent) {
		window.attachEvent("message", function(event) {
			if (event.data.length >= 22) {
				if (event.data.substr(0, 22) == "__MM-LOCATION.REDIRECT") location = event.data.substr(22);
			}
		}, false);
	}
</script>
</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>NOAA Emergency Response Storm Imagery</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/noaa-emergency-response-storm-imagery.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/noaa-emergency-response-storm-imagery.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/9/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-image.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="United States"/>
            <category term="US Federal"/>
            <category term="Data Source"/>

        <updated>2023-01-13T16:36:58-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/9/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-image.jpg" alt="" />
                    Who collected the data? This imagery was collected by NOAA's NGS (National Geodetic Survey) RSD (Remote Sensing Division). To meet NOAA's homeland security and emergency response requirements the RSD collects imagery over areas affected by major weather events with emergency declarations. This data is acquired rapidly&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/9/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-image.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h2><img loading="lazy" src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/assets/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-image.jpg" alt="aerial imagery extents over southwest florida 2022" data-is-external-image="true"></h2>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Who collected the data?</h2>
<p>This imagery was collected by NOAA's NGS (National Geodetic Survey) <a href="https://www.ngs.noaa.gov/RSD/rsd_home.shtml" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RSD (Remote Sensing Division)</a>. To meet NOAA's homeland security and emergency response requirements the RSD collects imagery over areas affected by major weather events with emergency declarations. This data is acquired rapidly and distributed to federal, state and local governments and is openly available to the general public.</p>
<div class="card">
<div class="card-body">
<blockquote class="blockquote mb-0">
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">"On September 29, the National Geodetic Survey (NGS) began collecting aerial damage assessment images in the aftermath of Hurricane Ian. Imagery is being collected in specific areas by NOAA aircraft, identified by NOAA in coordination with FEMA and other state and federal partners."</p>
<footer class="blockquote-footer"><cite title="Source Title"><a href="https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/news/sep22/ngs-storm-imagery-ian.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NOAA</a></cite></footer></blockquote>
<footer></footer><footer>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Why is the data important?</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">Aerial imagery can be expensive to collect and process over large areas and in emergency response situations it can be critical in making decisions. Having a federal agency be able to quickly collect, process and desseminate this critical data makes rescue response decision making more informed.</p>
<div class="card">
<div class="card-body">
<blockquote class="blockquote mb-0">
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">"NOAA's aerial imagery aids safe navigation and captures damage to coastal areas caused by a storm. Aerial imagery is a crucial tool to determine the extent of the damage inflicted by flooding, and to compare baseline coastal areas to assess the damage to major ports and waterways, coastlines, critical infrastructure, and coastal communities. This imagery provides a cost-effective way to better understand the damage sustained to both property and the environment."</p>
<footer class="blockquote-footer"><cite title="Source Title"><a href="https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/news/sep22/ngs-storm-imagery-ian.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NOAA</a></cite></footer></blockquote>
</div>
</div>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">How to access the data</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4"><a href="https://storms.ngs.noaa.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://storms.ngs.noaa.gov/</a></p>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">This link will take you to the index page with all of the <a href="https://storms.ngs.noaa.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emergency Response Imagery</a> links going back to 2003. The imagery can be viewed online with two different basemap options being MapBox Streets or MapBox Satelite to examine what areas looked like before the listed event. The data is also available for download with a "Download" button on the top menu bar. It is also possible to connect your own GIS to the data source via WMTS (Web Map Tile Service) by clicking "About" then "Web Services" for the link.</p>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Analyzing imagery from the Hurricane Ian 2022</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">Hurricane Ian hit southwest Florida in late September 2022. Using the <a href="https://storms.ngs.noaa.gov/storms/ian/index.html#9/26.4200/-81.9700" target="_blank" rel="noopener">online viewer</a> for Hurrican Ian aerial imagery we will look at some images of before and after the storm.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/assets/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-img-marina.jpg" alt="aerial imagery of a fort myers marina before the hurricane ian" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>A marina in Matanzas Pass in the Fort Myers area before hurricane Ian 2022.</figcaption></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/assets/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-img-marina-after.jpg" alt="aerial imagery of a fort myers marina after the hurricane ian" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>The same marina in Matanzas Pass after hurricane Ian 2022 showing destroyed docks and piled up boats.</figcaption></figure>
<p>We can clearly see massive damage to the marina and the boats that are docked there. It is also worth noting that the the dock and boats have been pushed up onto the mangrove forest to the right causing environmental damage.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/assets/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-img-rv-park-before.jpg" alt="aerial imagery of a fort myers rv park before the hurricane ian" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>A RV/Mobile home park in the Fort Myers Beach area before hurricane Ian 2022.</figcaption></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/assets/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-img-rv-park-after.jpg" alt="aerial imagery of a fort myers rv park after the hurricane ian" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>The same RV/Mobile home park after hurricane Ian 2022 showing extensive property damage.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Looking at this image you can cleary tell that just about every single building was washed away and destroyed within this mobile home and rv park. Thoughts and prayers go out to everyone that called this place home and we can only hope that they were able to evacuate to somewhere safer to wait out the storm.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/assets/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-img-placida-before.jpg" alt="aerial imagery of a placida residential area before the hurricane ian" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>A residential area in Placida before hurricane Ian 2022.</figcaption></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/assets/noaa-ngs-rsd-emergency-response-img-placida-after.jpg" alt="aerial imagery of a placida residential area after the hurricane ian" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>The same residential area in Placida after hurricane Ian 2022 showing property damage.</figcaption></figure>
<p>A quick glance shows that about about fifty to sixty percent of the houses sustained some damages while another twenty to thirty percent seem to be completely destroyed. It is no surprise that all of these coastal areas hit directly by the storm were damaged severly. There are no official figures yet but it is looking like Ian may be one of the worst hurricanes in history in terms of property damage costs.</p>
</footer></div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Contact Open Source GIS Data</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/contact-open-source-gis-data.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/contact-open-source-gis-data.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/7/contact-image.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="About"/>

        <updated>2023-01-18T15:27:33-05:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>About Open Source GIS Data</title>
        <author>
            <name>Parker Dinkins</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/about-open-source-gis-data.html"/>
        <id>https://opensourcegisdata.com/about-open-source-gis-data.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/6/about-us.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="About"/>

        <updated>2023-01-13T14:11:28-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/6/about-us.jpg" alt="" />
                    Purpose of Open Source GIS Data The purpose of this website is to provide a place for people to find and utilize open source GIS data. From local government sources to globally available sources, this is the place to find them and learn how they&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://opensourcegisdata.com/media/posts/6/about-us.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Purpose of Open Source GIS Data</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">The purpose of this website is to provide a place for people to find and utilize open source GIS data. From local government sources to globally available sources, this is the place to find them and learn how they can be used.</p>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">Topography, weather, hydrology, ecology, social, conflict, administrative and many more types of data are at your fingertips here.</p>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Special Thanks</h2>
<div class="card">
<div class="card-body">
<blockquote class="blockquote mb-0">
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">"If I have seen further it is by standing on the shoulders of Giants."</p>
<footer class="blockquote-footer"><cite title="Source Title">Sir Isaac Newton</cite></footer></blockquote>
</div>
</div>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">I want to thank Joseph from <a href="https://mappingsupport.com/">mappingsupport.com</a> for curating and maintaining his list of 3000+ ArcGIS rest servers. This list is one of the largest collections of federal, state, and local GIS data sources.</p>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">Next I would like to thank Ben Millard from <a href="https://servers.cartobin.com/about">cartobin.com</a> for creating a web application with an API using Joseph's list of sources. Using this API has allowed me to easily add thousands of sources to this website for every state and US Federal Agency.</p>
<h2 class="fw-bolder mb-4 mt-5">Start Exploring the World Through Different Lenses Using Open Source GIS Data Today</h2>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">Unlock new understandings of the world around you by exploring GIS data. GIS data goes beyond boring spreadsheets. View data using free applications or web portals and begin creating your own maps.</p>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">You never know what you might find until you start looking. Start by finding data around your local area or a topic you are interested in. Check out the home page for inspiration or click through the categories.</p>
<p class="fs-5 mb-4">Are you from the United States? Start exploring data sources from your state using the United States <a href="https://opensourcegisdata.com/state/index.html">Data Index</a> by using the map and clicking on your state. Explore the Geo Portals or by using the rest service link directly with you own GIS.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
